Guide to the International Association of Bridge, Structural, and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 0580 Records WAG.214
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 580 Records
1907,1938-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers. Local 580 (New York, N.Y.)
Lusardi, Dennis
WAG.214
47 Linear Feet in 47 record cartons and 3 folders.
The International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 580 (Ornamental and Architectural Iron Workers) was chartered in 1938, evidently as a result of the restructuring of an older local, Local 447; its members traditionally did non-structural iron work, for example, construction of stairs, trap doors, metal walls, fire escapes, metal cabinets and furniture and ornamental details. The New York iron workers' organization claimed to be the oldest in the trade, and was at one time affiliated with the Knights of Labor; its members worked on the Statue of Liberty and many other historic projects. Originally dominated by German, Jewish and Irish craftsmen, the local's membership became more diverse by the 1980s, as a result of court orders regarding affirmative action. The collection includes correspondence, financial records, subject files, reports, membership applications and withdrawals and court documents relating to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission findings and directives, photographs, ephemera, and artifacts.
Historical/Biographical Note
The International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 580 (Ornamental and Architectural Iron Workers) was chartered in 1938, evidently as a result of the restructuring of an older local, Local 447; its members traditionally did non-structural iron work, for example, construction of stairs, trap doors, metal walls, fire escapes, metal cabinets and furniture and ornamental details. The New York iron workers' organization claimed to be the oldest in the trade, and was at one time affiliated with the Knights of Labor; its members worked on the Statue of Liberty and many other historic projects. Originally dominated by German, Jewish and Irish craftsmen, the local's membership became more diverse by the 1980s, as a result of court orders regarding affirmative action.
Arrangement
This collection has not been processed by an archivist.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes correspondence, financial records, subject files, reports, membership applications and withdrawals and court documents relating to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission findings and directives, photographs, ephemera, and artifacts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Dennis Lusardi, on behalf of the International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, local 580, in 2001. The accession number associated with this gift is 2001.200.
Financial records; Reports.; Black-and-white negatives.; Black-and-white photographs.; Correspondence.; Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Artifacts (object genre); Printed ephemera.; Photographs.; Lusardi, Dennis; International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers. Local 580 (New York, N.Y.); International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers. Local 580 (New York, N.Y.); International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers; United States. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
- Correspondence, reports, and financial records of the organization. Mostly subject files organized alphabetically from Allied Building Metal Industries to Weekly Payroll Reports., 1942-1947 (Box 1)
- Contracts, publications, minutes, and other organizational records, 1938-1989 (Box 2)
- Subject files arranged alphabetically from Agreement-Independent Employers to Waivers. Also included is correspondence, reports, publications, financial records, and other organizational records, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, reports, and other organizational records., 1944-1986 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, legal records, and other organizational records, 1947-1996 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, reports, financial records, and other organizational records, 1982-1996 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, financial records, election records, and other organizational records, 1972-1983 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, financial records, and other organizational records, 1971-1980 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, reports, court documents, and other organizational records, 1978-1988 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, court documents, and other organizational records related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1987-1991 (Box 10)
- Correspondence and court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1990-1991 (Box 11)
- Correspondence and court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al.; financial and other organizational records, 1942-1990 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, financial records, and other organizational records, 1944-1946 (Box 13)
- Correspondence, reports, and other organizational records, 1941-1969 (Box 14)
- Correspondence, minutes, and other organizational records, 1941-1942 (Box 15)
- Manuals and other guides, 1989-1991 (Box 16)
- Subject files arranged alphabetically from Accident Reports to New York City Central Labor Council. Also includes material on the Office of Safety and Health Administration (OSHA) (Box 17)
- Subject files arranged alphabetically from New York State Building and Construction to OSHA. Also includes correspondence, records, and court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1979-1991 (Box 18)
- Correspondence, records, and court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Local 580, et al., 1978-1989 (Box 19)
- Correspondence, reports, records, and court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Local 580, et al., 1970-1989 (Box 20)
- Court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Local 580, et al. Also includes contracts, 1981-1990 (Box 21)
- Court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Local 580, et al. Also includes contracts, 1969-1992 (Box 22)
- Groups of subject files: One arranged alphabetically from Adding Machine Service Co. to General Correspondence, the second from Agreement with International to Withdrawal members. Also includes financial records, 1969-1976 (Box 23)
- Stewards weekly reports, 1978-1984 (Box 24)
- EEOC Employee Summary, 1994 (Box 25)
- Court documents related to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission v. Local 580, et al., 1988-1990 (Box 26)
- Correspondence, financial records, contract negotiations, and other organizational files, 1968-1972 (Box 27)
- Correspondence, publications, reports, and other organizational records primarily relating to Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1976-1984 (Box 28)
- Photographs, correspondence, reports, publications, clippings, and other organizational records. Also includes a t-shirt from union election, 1971-1978 (Box 29)
- Membership applications, financial records and other organizational records, 1975-1981 (Box 30)
- Daily sign in sheets, membership applications, and stewards weekly reports, 1979-1985 (Box 31)
- Daily sign in sheets, correspondence, reports, publications, and other organizational records, 1976-1986 (Box 32)
- Contracts, pamphlets, reports, and other organizational records, 1970-1984 (Box 33)
- Groups of subject files: One is arranged alphabetically from Allied Agreement to Underwood Corporation, the other from Auditor's Report to Withdrawal Cards Deposited. Also included are t-shirts, pamphlets, and stamps, 1967-1981 (Box 34)
- Military records and contracts, 1940-1967 (Box 35)
- Groups of subject files: One is arranged alphabetically from Agreement-Independent Employers to Misc. Government Forms, the other from Book Orders to Pension Members. Also included are correspondence, contracts, and other organizational records, 1965-1983 (Box 36)
- Correspondence, financial records, and other organizational records, 1967-1969 (Box 37)
- Groups of subject files: One is arranged alphabetically from Decisions on Metal Cabinets to Wage Increase, the other from Independent Agreement to Withdrawal Members. Also included are correspondence and other organizational records, 1955-1965 (Box 38)
- Correspondence, publications, and other organizational records primarily relating to the scholarship fund, 1955-1975 (Box 39)
- Groups of subject files: One is arranged alphabetically from Apprentice to Withdrawal Members, the other from Bldg. & Const. Trades Council to Withholding Tax Exemption Certificates. (Box 40)
- Correspondence, financial records, and other organizational records relating to the scholarship fund, 1971-1981 (Box 41)
- Correspondence and other organizational records relating to the scholarship fund. Also includes three volumes of defense exhibits from the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1970-1984 (Box 42)
- Forms and court documents related to the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al., 1970-1984 (Box 43)
- Forms and correspondence related to the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC) v. Local 580, et al. Also includes some meeting minutes., 1969-1972 (Box 44)
- Subject files arranged alphabetically from Change of Members' Name to Withdrawal Cards Deposited. Also includes correspondence and organizational files, 1972-1982; 1972 (Box 45)
- Correspondence, financial records, minutes, and other organizational records, 1967-1972 (Box 46)
- Subject files arranged alphabetically from Executive Board Correspondence to Workers Defense League, 1971 (Box 47)
- Photographs: Black and White Prints of the Construction of the Singer Sewing Machine Building at Broadway and Liberty Street, New York CIty, circa 1907 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  These prints are reproductions from a book, newspaper, or other printed material that was probably published not long after the completion of construction of the Singer Sewing Machine Building (1908).
- Photographs: Copy Negatives of Prints of the Construction of the Singer Sewing Machine Building at Broadway and Liberty Street, New York CIty, circa 1907 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 2)
  These copy negatives were shot from a book, newspaper, or other printed material that was probably published not long after completion of construction of the Singer Sewing Machine Building (1908). All or most of the photographic prints located in Folder 1 in Box A005 of the records of the International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers, Local 580 (WAG 214) were printed from this group of negatives.
- Ephemera and Artifacts: Stickers and Pins with Local 580 Logo or Logos and Slogans of Other Labor Unions, circa 1980s-1996 (Box Shared Tamiment A005, Folder 3)